OK, so this is the fourth lecture for Economics 252,
Financial Markets.
And I wanted to talk about some really basic concepts
about portfolios.
A portfolio is a collection of investments.
And I want to talk about
risk and return, and eventually get
into the core theory, which is the capital asset pricing
model in finance.
But first, I wanted to say something about last lecture.
Last time, I talked about innovation in finance.
And I presented finance as
a sort of branch of engineering
in a way.
We invent financial devices, and the devices serve certain
functions, and in order to serve those functions, they
have a number of details
that have to be gotten right.
Moreover, there's a process that we call the financial
market.
And the process of invention involves experimentation.
And when an experiment doesn't
work, we forget about it and
we move on.
But when it does work, it
gets copied all over the world.
So, I thought a nice
way to transition to today's lecture
would be to talk about
one very important moment in the
history of finance.
And that was when the first real important stock was
invented.
And it was, see if I
can spell it right, Verenigde Ostindische,
I might be misspelling this, Compagnie, 1602.
This was the first, did I get that all right?
So, that's Dutch for the United East India Company.
I think I got it right.
It was founded in that year.
It was a time when Holland
was at war, and the government was
worried about the economy, and
they were willing to experiment
with raising capital to keep the economy prospering.
And someone had this idea.
Let's start.
Let's get to it.
We have to start with this idea.
And I can't write this
in Dutch, but they created the
Amsterdam Stock Exchange.
And initially, it had only one stock.
And so, this is called VOC.
And it was a trading company.
They were going to set them
up, and they were going to
buy ships, and they were going
to sail all over the world, and
they were going to trade in various commodities.
So, it sounds pretty basic, but no one had
ever done this before.
So, it was a trading company.
They had a lot of business.
And the thing is, they only had one stock.
And so, they could make their own stocks.
And they were the only ones who had any stock.
And so, they were the only ones.
So, it's interesting how much
got invented in this one year,
First of all, they invented a corporate logo.
I don't know if I have it right.
It was something like V-O-C. I
don't know if I did that right.
Just like we would put on advertisements for a company
today.
Maybe more, but that's not very important.
But what's really important also
is that this was a long-term
venture.
OK?
There were lots of ventures already in Europe, where a
group of merchants would get together, and they would pool
their money for one trip.
They would send ships out,
and these ships would trade and
come back, and then they'd dissolve the whole thing.
But this was different.
This one was going to go indefinitely.
And in their initial announcement, they said, we're
going to set up operations all over the world.
We're going to have an office
in India and another one in
the Middle East.
And they said, we're going to
have a big one in, I don't
know, Indonesia.
And it's a big thing.
And in the New World, in America, but primarily East
India, from the name.
And so, the interesting thing
is, they set up a stock
exchange to trade shares in it.
And the stock exchange arranged so that you
could, you know, you could trade shares in it.
And the stock exchange arranged so
that you could trade shares in it.
And this was a typical idea.
And the stock exchange arranged so
that you could trade every day.
And so, there was lively trading.
And this was part of the idea.
Because when they set up
a company in those days, you
could get your shares when they founded
the company, and that was it, right?
I mean, you couldn't trade them.
Or maybe you could infrequently.
A company might open its books
once a year, and they would take
new shareholders in.
But someone had, hey, this is an idea.
Even though the VOC doesn't open its books regularly,
they would open it.
We can trade them every day.
What difference does it make?
So, we're going to have
stock brokers on the Amsterdam Stock
Exchange, and maybe they'll own some shares in VOC.
And then they'll have an inventory of shares.
And then somebody wants to buy some, you buy
them from the broker.
You don't have to contact the company.
And then the broker, maybe at
the year end, will report to
the company that you own the shares.
But it doesn't have to, right?
The broker does it.
So, the broker says, you own these shares.
You trust the Amsterdam Stock Exchange, because they have
rules and code of ethics.
So, you think you own, well,
you do own VOC shares, if you
buy them from a broker.
The VOC doesn't know it
yet, but you've got the shares,
because the broker is a member of the Amsterdam Stock
Exchange, and it says that you have the shares.
Then almost immediately after 1602, a funny thing happened.
Guess what it was?
The brokers started selling more shares than they had.
What's to stop them from doing that?
Some of them did that.
So the broker maybe owns some
shares in VOC, and he gets
lots of buyers, and the
broker ends up selling more shares
than he has.
And he thinks, well, I'll get them later.
And he says, what do my customers
care if they own shares that I don't
report to the company right away anyway?
I'll make good on this.
I'm a broker.
I know what to do.
I'll buy them later, and I'll get them.
So, you see what starts to happen?
There are more shares out
there being traded than there exist
in the company, because the broker is selling shares that
he doesn't own.
So, there began in way back,
even in this time, there began
what we call short-term trading.
Short-term trading.
Short sales or short interest.
I mean, it happens when you
set up a stock market and you
allow, well, we would call
it today street name, owning stocks
in street name.
We have stock exchanges, many stock exchanges in the world
today, and they, including, by the way, the Amsterdam Stock
Exchange is the only one.
It's the oldest stock exchange
in the world, and it's still
trading, but it has merged.
First, it merged with Brussels and Paris, and now they're
called Euro Next Amsterdam.
But they're still doing this.
Nothing stopped them in over 400 years.
They keep doing it.
But this stock exchange, and many others like it, allows
brokers to sell you stocks in
what's called, I don't know, a
street name.
And what that means is that
when you buy shares, the broker
puts in your account that you own these shares.
But the company doesn't know it, because the actual
ownership is registered in the name of the broker.
And so, the broker is selling shares.
And it's only through the
broker that you know that you
have shares.
So, the broker on the stock
exchange may be short, may have
sold more shares than he or she has.
That's all right.
It happened as long ago
as right from the beginning of
the stock market.
There was a scandal.
I was reading the history of this.
Who was the guy?
I don't know.
Isaac La Mer.
A Dutchman.
In 1609, he was not a broker.
He was a businessman.
He was able to sell more shares than he had.
So, he had negative.
A broker allowed him to do that.
And so, he had a short interest in VOC.
Massive short interest.
And people who own VOC shares started thinking, what's
going on here?
Someone is borrowing shares from a broker and selling
them.
And then, that tends to bring down the price.
And there was a downward movement in the Amsterdam
stock market, and this guy
was blamed for having shorted the
stock and forcing down the price.
And so, the Amsterdam Stock Exchange for two years, from
1609 to 1611, banned short selling.
But then they decided to let it go again.
The point of all this discussion, I'm telling you a
story about Holland four hundred years ago.
But the reason I'm telling you
this story is to try to
emphasize how certain things just happen naturally.
Once you set the framework up,
you set up a big company and
it's a company that lasts a long time, OK?
It's very valuable.
And anybody can buy shares in it.
So it's democratic.
And the value of this thing is,
if you just do this, there will
be a downfall.
And if you don't, then you will lose your money.
So it's not a bad strategy.
You need to understand that.
All right.
Likewise, it's not a good strategy.
Nobody wants to give up money.
It's not a good strategy.
Everybody should consider it.
And the value is very uncertain, because this
company is going to be
in business into the far future.
And it's building a whole arrangement, an empire of
trading posts and ships.
And who knows what it's worth?
So the price is very uncertain.
And buying it is a sort of a gamble.
And so the price starts fluctuating wildly.
And it attracts all kinds of interest.
And some people think it's
going to go up, and some
people think it's going to go down.
And they start debating about this and wondering about this.
And some guy like Isaac Lemaire thinks it's going to
go down, so he wants to short the stock.
He wants to sell.
He doesn't want to buy it, he
wants to short it, so he can
have a negative quantity.
Thank you.
Other people are really positive and excited about it.
And they want to buy all they can get.
And they want to even buy more than they have.
And they want to buy
the stock, because they have the
money to buy the stock.
So you have this tension between the shorts, like
Isaac Lemaire, and the gung-ho traders who want to buy.
And it creates a lot of volatility in the market.
But the whole effect of this
is to create interest in the
stock, so it brings in money.
And it ultimately made the VOC very successful.
Because so many people wanted
to give money to this trading
company.
So they were able to build
hundreds of ships and set up
big outposts all over.
And it became very valuable.
And it was an invention, kind of a social invention.
I'm thinking it's kind of analogous.
We have recent inventions that we think about.
The social media, we have Facebook and other
recent inventions.
This was an invention like that.
It was an invention.
It got people together and communicating and excited
about something.
And it created sort of a
game that people were playing that
turned out to be productive.
That's why it was copied all over the world.
So the core concepts, which we
began in Holland in 1609, are
everywhere now.
And every country of the world has this.
I should also add, by the way, that the
VOC was a limited liability corporation.
Amazing.
When I told you that limited
liability came in in 1811 in
New York, I think I qualified that.
It used to be that some companies had in their
charter an agreement with the government that the
stockholders had limited liability.
What came in in 1811 in New
York was a law that said, all
companies are a limited liability.
And moreover, anybody in the
world, anyone in New York, can
start a company.
And it will always be limited liability.
So don't worry.
You can invest in any company.
And you can not worry about being sued for the
debts of the company.
Well, back then, Holland didn't go that far, but they
did create one company that did have limited liability.
And so, what that meant was,
you could, you know, you're a
dehorser.
And I said, you could invest
in this company, and it's just
a game, you know?
I can't lose more than I put into it.
And if these guys turn out
to be crooks, and some of them
are hanged for their crimes, no problem with me, because
I'm an innocent investor.
The law says, law doesn't require that I investigate,
whether the guys who run the company are really honest.
Let's protect investors.
So all you can lose
is the money you put in.
And it created a tremendous opportunity.
It was talked about, because the
stock price went up and up
and up, and it made
people rich who invested in it.
But it was also very volatile.
It went up and down.
People had never seen anything like this before, because
nothing was so actively traded and had such an interesting
opportunity.
And it was something you
could change your mind about from
one day to the next.
And so, it was, anyway, I
didn't want to just tell a
story.
This is a story, though, that illustrates our last lecture.
It was a breakthrough innovation.
It was a kind of gambling, but not gambling.
It was gambling on real things.
And so, you know, people like
to gamble, but it's usually a
waste of their time.
This was setting up trade around the world.
And so, it was an important, very important innovation.
But now, I wanted to use it
as a lead-in to the main theme of
this lecture, which is about portfolio management and risk.
And the first concept I
wanted to talk about is leverage.
Leverage.
Leverage is a very important concept.
And also, let me add, the equity premium.
These are the two main concepts.
Maybe I'll do equity premium first.
Here's the conundrum that people were presented with.
And I'll stay in the VOC
story, but it's much more general than
that.
VOC, after a few years
out, people thought, you know, this
is amazing.
It's just growing so fast.
It's making so much money.
It might have a really high return, like unbelievably high,
like 20% a year or even more.
But let's say 20% a year.
And that's what generated the excitement.
But some people have wondered, well, how can it be?
Maybe it's earned 20%, but
how can it consistently do that?
And that's the real question.
So, let me put a puzzle.
We've gone through 400 years
of history since the VOC was
established.
And since then, it seems
to be remaining true that companies'
shares do extremely well.
And that's a puzzle.
Because, you know, if you can
make a high return on some
stocks, it's going to be very, very high.
And wouldn't you think that enough people would flock into
the investment, so that it
no longer, you know, there's too
many people trying to do this,
so it's no longer performing so
well?
But in fact, it seems like
the average return on stocks has
been very high.
This is a theme.
And I think that's the
reason why I'm talking about stocks
for the long run, which
I have on the reading list.
Siegel has data, doesn't go back
to 1602, but it goes back
to the 19th century.
And he says that the geometric average return, annual return
on the United States stock market from 1871
to 2006 was 6.8% a year, corrected for the
long run.
And that's 6.8% a year after inflation.
So, if you add a 3% or
4% inflation rate, that's 10% a year.
Let's compare that with short-term
governments, which are the safest
thing in the United States.
The average real return on
them was only 2.8% a year.
So, the difference is 4% a year.
So, for well over 100
years in the United States, stocks
performed extremely well.
Moreover, he points out, there
was no 30-year period since 1831
to 1861 when stocks underperformed either short-term
or long-term bonds.
So, the stocks underperformed.
So, the stocks have been good investments.
What do we make of that?
Don't people learn?
You know, think if people learn, they
would all want to do the good thing.
Why does anyone invest in something else?
That was the puzzle here.
It's not just a United States phenomenon.
The London Business School professors, Dimson, Marsh,
and Staunton wrote a book called, The
Triumph of the Optimists.
That is, optimists about the stock market.
And they looked at the equity premium
in many different countries around the world.
And they found that all of the countries,
and this is looking over much of the 20th
century, all of the countries had an equity
premium that the stocks did better than the
bonds of that country.
The lowest of the countries they studied,
they had the lowest of the bonds.
And the highest of the countries was Belgium,
which had an equity premium of only 3%.
And the highest was Sweden, which
had an equity premium of 6%.
So, that's an interesting question.
How can it be that some
asset, namely stocks, outperform all other assets?
Okay.
So, then that comes up then
to, what is the standard answer?
And the standard answer is risk.
Stocks are riskier.
The price jumps up and down from day to day.
So, you have a, the
extra return is a risk premium.
And so, that is what I
want to pursue today in this lecture.
Does that explain the answer?
Yes.
So, what is the equity premium?
And how should we think about the equity premium?
So, what I'm going to do is feature
the theory that was originally invented by Harry Markowitz
when he was a graduate
student at the University of Chicago.
And as a, or maybe it
was shortly after he was a student.
In 1952, he published a classic article
in the Journal of Finance that really changed
the way we think about risk in finance.
Changed it forever.
It gets back at this core idea.
You know, people looking at, going back to
the days of the VOC, people had the idea,
you know, I think stocks are the best investment.
And they were right.
They were right.
And so, they did it.
And I think that's what they were saying.
So, they were right.
They were saying, okay, I'm writing that
down and I'm putting it in quotation marks
because it's not a term that I would use.
What is the best investment?
Well, they said, look, the
VOC is just returning tremendous amounts.
Any smart person would just put as
much as he can into that investment.
Something seems wrong about that.
I mean, it can't be true that, well,
it's a great investment, but you know, it's just
a great investment.
It's a great investment.
But it's not a good investment.
It's not a good investment.
But it's a great investment.
It's a great investment.
So, what Markowitz, when I went back and
read his Journal of Finance article in 1952,
it's kind of remarkable to me, that what
he was talking about wasn't known yet in 1952.
He was given a lot
of information about how to invest.
He had a lot of information about how to invest.
He was getting at this
core idea of, what's the best
investment?
And how do you judge what's the best investment?
And judging from his article, to
me, it sounded so basic and
simple, of course, I've studied
finance, but it seemed odd to
me that everyone didn't know that in 1952.
So, let me, the question
is, I'll kind of paraphrase what
Markowitz said.
Let's imagine that you got
a job as a portfolio manager.
And you're kind of mathematically inclined, and
you know numbers and statistics, and you know how to
compute standard deviations and variances, things like that.
So, what is the first thing you do?
You're a scientist.
You're a numbers person.
You're a math person.
But now, imagine you've been entrusted with managing a
portfolio for some investor.
And the investor gives you a horizon.
Let's say you're managing it for one year.
And you're thinking, all right, what should I do?
Well, I want to collect
data on every possible investment I
could make, not just stocks and bonds, but real estate,
commodities, whatever.
And I can, for each of
these, I can compute what the average
return is.
I can compute what the average return was on those
investments.
And I can compute the
variance, and I can compute the
covariance and the correlation.
So, Markowitz, do you see it?
So, I've got all the data.
Now, I could say, I don't believe these data are
relevant to the future, because I'm smarter.
I can predict that some
company is going to do better
than it did in the past,
or some asset class will do
better than it did in the past.
But let's step back.
Let's think like a mathematician here, all right?
Let's just take as given all the historical average returns
and variances and covariances.
So, Markowitz says, well, what's the best portfolio,
given that, OK?
I could compute all these numbers.
What's the best assembly of all these things?
And you know, he realized
that nobody had ever thought that.
Isn't that a well-defined problem?
I give you all the variances.
I give you all the covariances.
I give you all the average returns.
And I say, let's just assume
that this is going to continue
like this.
What should I do as an investor?
And it's funny, Markowitz said,
he won the Nobel Prize later,
and deservedly, I think.
This was a breakthrough idea.
But he said, as a
graduate student, he was chatting with
someone in the hallway and thinking about this.
And he said, it suddenly hit me as an epiphany.
If I have these statistics, I
ought to be able to compute the
optimal portfolio.
It's mathematical, right?
It's just one thing.
I mean, what is the optimal portfolio?
It took him like two or
three days to figure the whole thing
out.
And I, you know, it's almost
like I could, haven't I set up
in your mind, do you see the problem?
You can figure this out, too, right?
I think, if you put your ingenuity onto it.
The funny thing is, nobody thought about it before
Markowitz.
So, actually, I was intrigued by that.
So, I went back trying to
find what people were talking about
before 1952.
And we have a new thing
on the web, relatively new, called,
do you ever play with this?
It's called ngrams.google.com.
It's a great thing.
It's a great tool.
And it's called ngramslabs.com.
And what you can do is, you
can put in any phrase you want
and search it for the,
it goes back like 400 years.
In English.
You can't do Dutch.
I don't think, maybe you can do Dutch, too.
I didn't try.
And you can search to see
what people were talking about in
books.
Because they have all these books scanned in now.
Now you can search for keywords.
You can search for keywords.
And you can do research on portfolio analysis.
That's what this is all about, right?
Figuring out what the optimal portfolio of stocks, bonds,
commodities is.
Hardly anyone even used the term before 1952.
I guess it didn't exist.
There was no theory of, you
kind of, how could that be?
I mean, you had all these sophisticated banks and
finance, they had no theory of portfolio analysis.
You had no theory of portfolio return.
It all started with Harry Markowitz.
Again, this is another testimony to how there are
sudden breakthroughs.
It should have been obvious.
But somehow, people didn't think.
But then I found one thing, though.
I did search on Ngrams on eggs in one basket.
There's an old adage, don't put
all your eggs in one basket.
It's kind of what we're coming to with Markowitz here.
He's got a whole theory of it.
But I found a, where was it?
I found an investment manual from 1874.
I can't find it here.
I'm not, this is from a book, 1874, about investing.
There is an old saying that
it is inadvisable to put all your
eggs in one basket.
So, it was already in the, and he says diversify.
And then he's done.
He doesn't tell you, how do you diversify?
How do I know what I should do?
It just stops there.
There was no theory of risk until 1952.
So, let's think about that.
You see the concept I have?
You know all the variances.
This isn't a judgment thing.
You know all the covariances.
What should I do?
Well, the first thing I want
to talk about is the very simple
case of pure logic.
Pure logic.
Pure leverage.
Let's go back to 1602, OK?
And there's only one stock.
That's VOC.
OK?
And there has to be something else.
Otherwise, there's nothing.
The other thing I'm going
to say is, there's an interest
rate, riskless interest rate.
So, I can invest in,
let's say, Dutch government bonds, which
are completely safe.
Of course, you might say, they're not completely safe,
but they're much safer than VOC.
VOC was wild.
The price was going all over the place.
So, let's, as an approximation,
say there's an interest rate.
You can borrow and lend at the interest rate.
And we'll call the riskless rate R sub f.
OK?
So, let's say that's 5% a year.
We're investing for one year.
So, I can invest at the interest rate.
And this is a boring investment.
It's just getting interest.
It's 5%.
But I can also borrow at the interest rate.
There's a market rate, and I can borrow at 5%.
You know, in practice, I would
probably have to pay a little
bit more as a borrower than
I could get as an investor.
But let's assume that away.
It's just an interest rate.
And anybody who wants to can
borrow and lend at the interest
rate.
I'll make it 5%, just for a round number.
OK?
And let's say VOC, the Dutch
East India Company, has had a
historic average return of 20%.
This is a spectacular investment, all right?
But let's say it's, so that's its mean.
It's mu, the mean of the investment.
But let's say it's really risky.
So, the standard deviation is 40%.
OK?
So, what can I do?
Suppose I have only, this is
a, let's do the simple problem
first, OK?
I have only one asset,
VOC, and I have riskless debt.
So, one thing I can do,
I'm going to draw a chart here
showing, OK, and I'm going
to do sigma on this axis.
And R on this axis.
So, sigma is the standard deviation of my portfolio.
OK?
And R is the expected return on the portfolio.
Now, all I'm going to do
is choose mixtures of the stock
and the, and the portfolio.
And I'm going to do the
same thing with the riskless rate.
So, I, a couple of points I
can read, I'm going to plot what
the available options are.
I, I can, I can see right
here that I can invest at 5%, right?
The riskless rate, and then I'll have no risk.
So, do you see this?
This is R sub F.
This is zero.
OK?
And these are positive numbers.
See what I've plotted here?
This is just the, the most boring investment.
Because there's no risk at all, and I'm earning 5%.
I can also plot this one, right?
So, here is VOC.
Is this big enough for you to see back there?
OK.
So, VOC is up here, and this
is 20, this is a risk of, I'm
at, of 40.
And the standard deviation of 20.
I'm sorry, expected return of 20
and a risk of 40, right?
So, those are two points, but
I can do other things, too.
What if I borrowed money to
buy, let's say I have 100 guilders.
I'm talking Dutch, OK?
That was the currency of the time, the guilder.
I'll write it for you.
Gilder.
OK.
So, I have 100 guilders to invest.
I could put it all in VOC stock, and I
would get, I would expect to get 20 guilders profit,
and I'd have a standard deviation of 40 guilders, right?
But what if I said, I'm
going to actually borrow another 100 guilders.
I only own 100 guilders, but I'm going
to borrow another 100 guilders and put it in
VOC stock.
So, that means I'll own 200 guilders.
I'm going to borrow another 100 guilders, and I'm going to have 200
guilders of VOC stock, and I'm going to have a debt of 100 guilders.
So, what's my expected return there?
Well, my expected return is going to be 35%, because,
look, I'm owner of 200 guilders worth of VOC stock.
The expected return is 20%, so I'm
going to get 40 guilders out of that.
But then I have a debt.
I've got to pay 5 guilders to my lender.
So, it's 35 is what I've got.
And as a percent of my initial investment, that's 35%.
So, I've got another point out here with,
this is 35, and down here is 80.
See, my standard deviation is 80 guilders now, right?
Because I have $200, and the
standard deviation was 40%, all right?
So, this is.
So, here I am two
for one, two for one leveraged.
I have $100, but I've put $200 in the stock.
Okay?
It's easy to do.
You know, you could do this in 1602.
So, you know, you can see how I knew it.
Obviously, I can, this is a straight line here.
I could do anything along this straight line.
And like here would be putting half of my
money in the riskless asset and half into VOC.
This would be putting one and a half,
150 guilders in VOC and borrowing 50 guilders.
You see, I can go
out as far as I want.
Then there's another branch to this.
What if I short 200?
I can go out and I
have 200 guilders of VOC stock.
Okay?
So, I go to the broker and
I say, I want to sell VOC stock.
I don't own any.
And the broker would say, all right, fine.
I'll lend you some shares.
And then you can sell them,
but you owe me the shares.
All right?
So, then I have minus
200 guilders worth of VOC stock.
And I'll hold that.
Oh, meanwhile, by the way, the broker says, after you sell the shares,
I will get 200 guilders from the person who bought them from you.
And I'll hold that and
I'll pay you interest on that.
Okay?
So, what do I get?
I expect to lose 40 guilders, because
I got $200, 200 guilders of the stock.
But meanwhile, I've got my original 100 guilders.
And now I've got another 200.
And they're all there earning interest at 5%.
So, I will get 15 guilders.
So, the expected return is
15 minus 40 or minus 25.
So, that's this point down here.
But you can see that you can
also do anywhere you like on that line.
So, what we have here is a broken straight line.
I can get anything I want.
Right?
This is kind of obvious right now.
Anywhere I want on that line.
On that broken straight line.
And I can do that.
So, here's where you get saying,
what is the optimal portfolio anyway?
I can get any return I want.
You know, my client who's asking me
to invest says, I want 100% return expected.
You say, got it.
I'm no genius, right?
I'm just doing the most obvious thing.
Anyone who wants 100% return can get it by genius.
I'm just going to leverage.
So, this is what, so then I create an investment.
If I have an investment company that
merely buys VOC stock and leverages it,
my investment company can have
any expected return that you want.
So, this is what Markowitz was wondering about.
Well, what does it mean
to have the optimal investment anyway?
And the core thing that he talked about
in 1952 is, there is no better portfolio.
There is no better portfolio.
There is no investment.
There is no best investment.
There is only a tradeoff between risk and return.
And we have to think about the best tradeoff.
And in this case, I've shown the tradeoff here.
It's this, this is what you can get.
And any one of those points is available.
And so, anyone who wants to invest with
you has to choose between risk and return.
There's no optimal portfolio in the fundamental sense.
There's no better portfolio in the fundamental sense.
And that's the matter of an optimal tradeoff.
And you know, nobody knew that before 1952.
So, let me just show you formally
this, what I just did on the blackboard.
You can say, we're going to
put, I've switched to dollars from Gilders.
Now, we're in the USA.
And so, put dollars in a risky
asset, x dollars in a risky asset,
1 minus x dollars in the riskless asset.
And the value of the
return on the portfolio is r.
That's equal to x r1
plus 1 minus x times rf.
It's linear.
That's because that's how expected values work.
The variance is x squared
times the variance of the return.
And so, if I want to write the portfolio
standard deviation as a function of the expected return,
I solve for x.
So, I'm taking this equation for x,
solve for x in terms of r.
So, x equals r minus
rf all over r1 minus rf.
And then I substitute that in to this equation.
Well, I want to take the square
root of it, because this is sigma squared.
And so, I've got sigma equals
r minus rf times r1 minus rf.
Well, actually, I have these absolute value marks.
And I always take the, if that's
negative, I switch sign and make it positive.
So, that gives the formula for
this broken straight line right here.
So, that's pretty simple.
That's the expected value.
Well.
Now, I want to move ahead, move on from this
simple idea to, we haven't really gotten fully into Markowitz yet.
Because this is a very simple story.
By the way, this broken straight line is
what we call a degenerate case of a hyperbola.
You know the, remember in math?
Hyperbola.
A curve.
A certain mathematical curve.
And we're seeing a hyperbola here.
But I'm going to show
you other hyperbolas in a minute.
What Markowitz really said, well, okay, this is simple.
This is, just pure leverage
is a simple thing to understand.
By the way, it's also
called gearing in the United Kingdom.
But let's think about now.
Suppose I have more than one risky asset.
Let's get past the year 1602.
And let's think about assets in a more modern context.
I want to move to another
example, which is two risky assets.
Now, let's think about this.
Now, we've moved past 1602,
and now we have two stocks.
And for the moment, I'm going to forget about leverage.
And let's just say, you can
put X1 in the first risky asset.
That's stock number one.
And I can put 1 minus
X1 in the second risky asset.
That's stock number two.
Okay?
So, what do I get here?
The expected, the portion of the stock.
And the portfolio expected return is just
the linear combination of the two expected returns.
So, R1 is the expected return on the first stock.
And R2 is the expected return on the second stock.
And you just, well, actually, I'm assuming
you have $1 to invest in this example.
I'm sorry.
I was assuming you had 100 guilders over there.
Now, I've just made it $1.
Unrealistically small amount.
But I just wanted a nice number.
Okay?
So, let's say $1 is 100
guilders, and then I haven't changed anything.
Okay.
So, I have one, see, I start out with $1.
So, if I put X1 dollars in the first one,
I have 1 minus X1 left for the other one.
So, it's very simple.
And this is the formula for the
variance of the portfolio, which we saw, essentially,
we saw that in the second lecture.
So, what I can do is go through the same
sort of exercise I did there with two risky assets.
All right?
And so, what I want to do
is draw a curve, something like this.
But I'll solve for X1 in terms of
R, just like I did for the riskless asset.
And I'll plug it into the equation for the variance.
I'll have to take the square root of that.
And I can plug it in.
And I can plot that.
Okay?
And you might think it would look something like that.
Well, it's not going to look
exactly like that, because it's risky.
Something's risky.
So, I did that.
And incidentally, on your problem set, you're going
to have to think about issues like this.
But what I did is, I took data on the average
return for the U.S. stock market, as measured by the S&P 500,
and the variance.
And then, the alternative investment I took
was 10-year treasuries for the United States government.
Long-term, because they're 10 years.
But we're only investing for one year.
So, they're risky, because the
market price goes up and down.
They're not riskless.
I call those bonds.
There's other kinds of bonds.
And I computed the relationship between the
standard deviation of the portfolio, and the risk.
Okay?
So, I computed the relationship between the standard deviation of the portfolio,
and the standard deviation, and the expected return, just as I showed you.
Again, using data from 1983 to 2006.
And it kind of looks like this curve, doesn't it?
Except, this is a degenerate parabola.
But it looks like this.
Right?
It's a hyperbola.
I said it wrong.
Hyperbola.
You know how hyperbola, do you remember this from math?
Hyperbolas, well, they look like that, and
they approach asymptotes, which are straight lines.
So, here is the hyperbola for stocks and bonds.
So, just as I had a
point here, which represented 100% VOC,
I can have over here a
point, which represents 100% U.S. stocks.
Okay?
And I can take another point,
which is 100% bonds, that's here.
This point is 25% stocks, 75% bonds.
This point is 50% stocks, 50% bonds.
Okay?
And I can see that this is the choice set
that I, as an investor, have between stocks and bonds.
Okay?
So, is that clear?
Is that any?
So, again, there's no, you
see, all these are different portfolios.
If you're just going to do stocks and bonds and nothing else,
what you choose to do depends on your taste, on your risk tolerance.
I could go 100% stocks, but I'm
going to have a lot of risk.
I'm going to have a nice expected return.
It looks like it's about 13%, 14%.
But I'm going to have a high variance.
It looks like it's about 18%.
This is the S&P 500 stock market.
And so, it has a lot of variance.
I could be safe and
I could go all in bonds.
I could be here.
Then I'd have, you know, a lower, much
lower return, but I have a lower variance.
So, what should I do?
Well, what do you learn from this?
First of all, you learn
there isn't any single optimal portfolio.
But, you know, you can do it.
You can do it.
But there is something.
Let's talk about being a 100% bond investor.
What do you think of that?
Is that a good idea?
You'd get this point right here.
Well, you definitely should not be a 100% bond investor.
That's one thing we just learned.
Why is that?
Because if I go up here, I have no more.
See, that's the same standard deviation, the same risk.
I have a higher return.
Right?
Higher expected return.
So, what did we just learn?
We learned that if you just stay in this
space of stocks and bonds, maybe you could be a
100% stock investor, but never in a million
years should you ever even think of being
a 100% bond investor.
Okay?
Because, look, it's just simple math.
I can figure it out.
I can figure out that I get
a higher expected return and no more risk.
So, this is lesson number one that Markowitz showed us.
Amazing.
It's so simple and obvious, right?
It's not so simple, because at the time
Markowitz wrote, Yale University was probably a 100%
bond investor, believe it or not.
They couldn't figure it out in those days.
So, we've made progress.
That's why I think Markowitz is among the
most deserving of the Nobel Prize winners in economics.
This is really basic.
It actually intrigues me.
I don't know how much you like math, but
going back to my childhood, I was interested in geometry.
These simple mathematical curiosities like
hyperbola are just fascinating to me.
It goes back to Apollonius of Perga, writing in
around 200 BC, wrote a book on conic sections.
And he wrote,
he invented the word hyperbola, parabola, ellipse.
So, I was thinking of looking back at his book, I
think it still survives, and seeing what he says about finance.
But I can be sure, he had no
idea that his theory would apply to finance.
I wish I could go back in
a time machine and talk to him.
He would be so happy to know that his theory of conic
sections, you know, it ended up applied to astronomy by Kepler and Newton.
And now it hits into finance.
Isn't it amazing how there's a unity of thought?
And this simple diagram has
just taught us something about investing.
That's not obvious.
Not obvious until you think about it.
I've just told you, never invest only in bonds.
But it doesn't tell you how much stocks and
how much bonds to, once you're above this point,
it seems to be a matter of taste.
It isn't any single decision that you can make.
So, now I want to move to a
more complicated world, where we have three assets.
Okay.
We're starting from, we had one
risky asset, then we had two.
Now, let's go even further.
Let's say three risky assets.
Well, the expected return is the same.
It's the weighted average.
Now, we have three weights.
X1, X2, and X3.
And they have to sum to one dollar.
I could have written X3
as 1 minus X1 minus X2.
I wrote it differently here.
It looked messy to write it the other way.
And this is the formula for the portfolio variance.
It's the X1 squared times the variance
of the return on the first risky asset,
plus X2 squared times the variance of
the return on the second risky asset,
plus X3 squared times the variance of
plus X2 squared times the variance of
the return on the third risky asset.
And then you have three more terms representing covariances.
You have to take account
of the covariances of the asset,
because if they move together, if they all
go in the same direction at the same time,
that's going to make your portfolio riskier.
And so, that's the portfolio variance.
And the portfolio expected return is
just, why didn't I write it there?
It's X1 R1 plus X2 R2 plus X3 R2.
Where the sum of the X's is 1, $1.
So, it's something that you can do
to calculate what is the optimal portfolio.
So, I decided to add
a third asset to my diagram.
The pink line up here is the
same, we call that an efficient portfolio frontier.
I have that in the title of the slide.
For stocks and bonds.
That's the pink line here.
But I've added the efficient portfolio
frontier for three stocks, three assets.
Stocks, bonds, and oil.
Oil is an important investment,
because our economy runs on it.
And the total value of oil in the ground is
comparable to the value of the stock markets of the world.
So, it's big and important.
So, let's put that in.
And what I have actually here is the minimum variance
mixture for any given return, expected return for the three assets.
And you can see that it's possible when you add a
third asset, oil, to bring the efficient portfolio frontier to the left.
And that's not the problem, because we've got
another asset, and it's also paying a good return.
And it's not correlated very much.
Oil doesn't correlate very much with the stock market.
So, we're spreading the risk out over more assets.
We're putting more eggs in our basket.
Okay.
And so, then we are,
we have a better, a better.
Yeah.
A better choice set now, right?
We can pick any point on that blue line.
And so, we shouldn't just have stocks and bonds.
We've learned we should have stocks, bonds, and oil.
We're lending, we're leading toward a fundamental insight, which
is due to Markowitz, which is, the more the merrier.
The more different kinds of assets you can put in, the lower
you can get the standard deviation of your return for any given interest.
Okay.
And so, the more you can get the standard
deviation of your return for any given expected return.
And so, the better off you are.
So, this is diversification.
So, while diversification was applauded in the 19th century,
no one had ever done the math like this before.
And now, we can see that you, when you do
the math, you want to have all three in your portfolio.
And yet, people don't know that.
They don't.
And so, there's an emotional resistance to this implication.
I once went to the government of Norway, gave a talk
at their Norges Bank, which is the central bank of Norway.
And I told them in my talk, I calculate that
Norway has something like 70% of its portfolio in oil.
I don't remember the exact number,
but it was something close to that.
Why do they have so much in oil?
Well, because they have the North Sea oil.
And so, I asked them at the bank,
don't you realize, where are you on this portfolio?
You're not on the frontier.
What Norway should be doing is something like 15%.
They could pick this point, right?
That would be reasonable.
15% oil, 53% stocks, 32% bonds,
which would give them that point.
Or they could pick this one.
I have a point labeled up here.
That's 21% oil, 79% stocks, no bonds.
All right?
Those are all choices, depending on your risk.
But they're not going to just pick 100% oil.
That would be way over here, much higher risk.
So, I asked them about that.
Why do you do this?
And I don't know if I got a good answer from them,
but basically, it was, well, we don't want to sell the oil,
because it's our national oil.
We don't want to sell
it because it's our national heritage.
We own it.
And I said, well, you don't have to sell it.
You can just do a derivative transaction.
You can short the futures market
for oil and reduce your exposure.
And then they said, well, some people
have mentioned that, but it's politically difficult.
So, they're not doing it.
Maybe next year, maybe the next government will do that.
So, they still aren't there yet.
They're not managing their risks well.
But it's a powerful and important thing.
Because if the market for oil
collapses, Norway is in big trouble.
They're not diversifying enough.
I don't mean to put them down.
They're smart people.
But like in any country, I
did the same thing with Mexico.
I went to the Banco de Mexico, and I
talked to Guillermo Ortiz, when he was director of it.
Same thing.
Mexico is not as dependent on oil as Norway is.
But it's a big problem.
I think, it's not so obvious for Mexico.
But it is politics that came in.
The question of, are you really saying Mexico should go into the futures
market and take a massive short position of billions of dollars of oil?
Again, it was like, this isn't reality.
We're not going to do that.
But I tried to make the point.
I think, it's a big problem.
Now, another thing is, so
I have shown here three assets.
The pink line is irrelevant.
Once we realize we have three assets.
We have stocks, bonds, and oil.
So, you should choose on this curve.
And of course, you should never
take down here, even though that's possible.
In other words, you could say, what portfolio
would give me 9% return with the least risk?
Well, it turns out it's 100% bonds.
But I just told you.
It's 100% bonds.
Because you can go up to this point.
So, you never do down here.
So, the efficient portfolio frontier is really the
part of the hyperbola that's above the minimum variance.
And you don't want to do minimum variance either.
This is the lowest possible risk portfolio.
You can't get down to zero risk
if all of your assets are risky.
So, you're stuck here.
But that's not necessarily the best thing.
Because people don't know.
They don't know.
And that's not the best thing.
Because people allow some risk.
This is having the minimum risk.
But I can get my return
up much higher without taking much risk.
So, I'd probably do that.
Okay.
Now, I can do this with more than three assets.
I can do it with 1,000 assets.
Now that we have computers.
Back in 1952.
I erased it.
But I had 1952 here.
Markowitz had to do it all by hand.
But now that we have computers, it's so easy.
You know, there are all kinds of programs.
In fact, on your problem set, we have Wolfram Alpha.
And it's a great tool.
It's a great tool.
And it's a great tool to do
calculations for you, for its own data.
So, these are easy to do now.
But what I want to do
now is add the riskless asset.
So, what we've done with the
blue line takes three risky assets.
It looks at only at assets
with a standard deviation greater than zero.
Now, I want to do the
optimal portfolio when there are four assets.
So, I've got all risky.
And now I have the thing that isn't risky.
It would be your one-year governments.
Right?
It's not risky because the
maturity matches my investment horizon.
I know exactly what I'm going to get.
It's 5%, let's say.
So, what can I do investing in these four assets?
Well, here it goes back to what
I did over here with this simple diagram.
I can pick any portfolio on the efficient portfolio
fund here and consider that as if that were VOC.
Right?
And then I can compute just how leverage allows me
to combine that with the riskless asset and that portfolio.
So, I can pick a point,
like I can pick this point here.
And then I could achieve by combining
that portfolio, which is 15% oil, 53% CTO.
And then I could combine that
with any amount of risky debt.
And I would get a straight line going
between, actually this diagram doesn't show zero on it.
I should have maybe done it differently, but between 5%.
So, actually that point right here,
I can do it on this diagram.
That point here is like
12% expected return and 8% variance.
So, I can do that.
It would be some, well, it would be here,
except this would be 12% and this would be 8%.
I can pick any point, and this would be 5%.
Any point along the straight
line connecting those points is possible.
So, what do I want to do if I have, I
want to get the highest expected return for any standard deviation.
I want to take a line that
goes through 5% on the Y axis.
And is as high as possible.
So, I'm taking a point right over here at 5%.
And trying to get as high as I can.
It turns out then, that I want to pick the
point which has a tangency with the efficient portfolio frontier.
And so, that means the highest straight
line that touches the efficient portfolio frontier.
And so, now I can
achieve any point on that line.
And that's, again, Markowitz's insight.
So, if I were to pick that point,
I would be picking, what does it look like?
I don't have it indicated.
It's probably something like 11% oil, 30% stocks, 50%.
Something like that.
It doesn't add up.
And that would be holding no debt.
But I could get even higher return,
if my client wants that, by leveraging.
I would borrow and buy
even more of this risky portfolio.
So, this portfolio here is called the tangency portfolio.
And what Markowitz's theory shows is that, once you add the risky
asset, the relevant efficient portfolio frontier is now really this tangency portfolio.
And so, I want to do a mixtures of the riskless
asset and the tangency portfolio that accords with my risk preferences.
But I don't want to ever just
move to one of these other portfolios.
So, these other portfolios, like 15%
oil, 53% stocks, 32% bonds, is dominated.
It has a high risk-free portfolio.
It's dominated.
It has a higher expected return for the same risk by a
portfolio of the tangency portfolio leveraged up a little bit by borrowing.
And similarly, well, yeah.
And so, this is, then it comes out.
And this is the, I don't know if it was
clear in Markowitz's paper, but it became clear soon after.
There really is, in a sense, an optimal portfolio.
It's the tangency portfolio.
Because everyone wants to invest on this line.
And that point is a, any point on this line
is a mixture of the riskless asset and the tangency portfolio.
And so, everyone wants to invest in the same portfolio.
So, there is an optimal portfolio, in a sense.
Which, it's, and I'm not saying it's a perfect portfolio.
But it's a portfolio in the sense that
everybody wants to do the same risky investments.
People will differ in their risk preferences.
And so, some of them will want
to do a riskier, a more leveraged version.
And some of them will do a
less leveraged version of the tangency portfolio.
But everyone wants to do the tangency portfolio.
And so, that is the
key idea of Markowitz portfolio management.
And it's been expressed by
some as the mutual fund theorem.
First of all, I have to just
define for you, what is a mutual fund.
You might not know that.
A mutual fund is a certain kind
of investment company aimed at a retail audience.
They could have just called
this the investment company theorem.
But history, I can't tell you
the history of thought on this.
It's, a mutual fund is a certain
kind of investment company that is mutual.
It means that the owners of the shares
in the fund are, there's no other owners.
It's just one class of investors.
All of, they're all equal, so it's mutual.
But that's irrelevant to you.
The idea is that all
we need is one mutual fund.
There's thousands of mutual funds to serve investors.
Because I had that everyone
is investing in the tangency portfolio.
So, they should call their fund the tangency portfolio fund.
And our fund is the optimal mix
of stock, bonds, oil, and whatever else.
And then, you don't necessarily want
to own only that mutual fund.
But you want to own mixtures of
that mutual fund and the riskless asset.
So, everyone holds, you only need one investment company.
So, this is the other, I told you this story.
I said, imagine that you have a mutual fund.
You were mathematically inclined and you have all
the statistics, and you're going to figure it out.
What's the best thing to do?
We've just figured it out.
I haven't gone through all the math details.
There is a best thing to do.
You should offer, as your
investment product, the tangency portfolio.
And that's it.
Once you've figured it out, there's nothing more to do.
There's no need to hire anymore finance people.
You've figured it out, according to Markowitz theory.
And all the investors in the world will do it.
And that's it.
All the investors in the world
will just invest in this one.
And that's case closed.
We don't need thousands of mutual funds.
Under the assumptions of Markowitz, which is that we're
agreed on the variances and covariances and expected returns.
There's a single optimal risky portfolio.
And then, the instructions to investors are very simple.
All you need is two assets in your portfolio.
You need a mutual fund that owns the tangency portfolio.
And whatever amount of debt you want.
So, if you're footloose and fancy
free, you can even leverage it.
You can borrow two to one, three
to one, it's up to your tastes.
But you don't need to look
at anything other than the mutual fund.
So, that's an important insight.
And what it means then
is, that leads to something else.
So, Markowitz didn't get this idea.
It came out later.
So, someone was thinking, well, if everyone
should be investing in the same portfolio,
it doesn't add up unless that portfolio is equal
to the total assets out there in the world.
Right?
If there's twice as much oil as there is stock,
then there has to be twice as
much oil as stock in the tangency portfolio.
Otherwise, it doesn't add up. Right?
Because everyone has to own everything.
Supply and demand have to equal.
So, it means, the mutual fund theory implies,
that the market portfolio equals the tangency portfolio.
And the market portfolio equals the tangency portfolio.
And now, I've pretty much finished the theory.
I should say, it implies, if
investors follow this model that we're having,
that they all want to, the Markowitz model,
if all investors think like Markowitz says,
they all want to do the same thing.
They all want to invest in the same best portfolio.
But the market portfolio is the same.
So, the market portfolio is the same.
So, the tangency portfolio equals the market portfolio.
So, I was saying earlier,
why is it that everyone doesn't invest in VOC stock?
How does it add up, right?
If VOC stock is just better than something else,
then that suggests everyone wants to
put all their money in VOC stock.
But we're realizing, they don't.
And they want to hold some proportion
of VOC stock and the riskless asset.
It has to add up, so that the market
is cleared and all the VOC stock is owned.
And more generally, if there are many assets,
all the assets have to end up owned by someone.
And so, the cardinal implication of this theory is that
the market portfolio, which is everything that's
out there in the world to invest in,
has to be protected.
Has to be proportional to the tangency portfolio.
And so, one of the implications is, if that's true,
and I'm done with my, I
have just a couple more slides here.
Let me go to here.
The capital asset, now it's called
the capital asset pricing model in finance.
So, that's capital asset, which is pricing model.
Which was not invented by Markowitz,
but was invented by Sharp and Lintner,
somewhat shortly after Markowitz.
The capital asset pricing model, and
I'm not going to derive this equation,
but it says the expected return
on any asset, the i-th asset,
equals the risk-free rate.
Plus the beta of that asset times the
difference between the expected return on the market
and the expected return on the risk-less asset.
I was just going to try to
explain this intuitively, and then I'll be done.
I have one more slide about the Sharpe ratio.
But the intuitive idea, let me just
say, everything should have a very simple explanation.
The intuitive idea is this.
Starting from Markowitz, we got
an understanding of what risk is.
And people didn't clearly appreciate that.
People used to think that
risk was uncertainty, right, in finance.
That if a stock has a lot of
uncertainty, that uncertainty means that it's a dangerous stock,
and people will demand a high expected return.
Otherwise, they won't hold the stock.
But the CAPM says, no, people don't
care about the uncertainty of the stock.
Because if it's one stock out of
many, they'll put it in their portfolio,
and if it's independent of everything
else, it all gets averaged out.
And so, who cares?
So, people don't care about variance.
Well, what is it that people care about?
People care about covariance.
Risk, this is the basic
insight that followed from Markowitz.
People care about how much
a stock moves with the market.
Because that's what costs me something.
I don't care if I could own a
million little stocks that all have independent variance.
It all averages out, doesn't mean anything to me.
I'll put them in tiny quantities in my portfolio.
But if they correlate with the market,
I can't get rid of the risk.
Because it's the big picture risk.
That's what insurance companies,
that's what everyone cares about.
It's this market risk, the big risk.
You only care about how much a stock
correlates with the big picture in its risk.
So, that's measured by beta.
And beta is the regression, the slope coefficient when you regress
the return on the i-th asset on the return of the market.
So, high beta stocks are
stocks that go with the market.
So, we found out that Apple has
a beta of 1.5 or roughly that.
That means they respond in an exaggerated way.
It's not one, it's greater than one.
They more than move with the market.
And so, investors will demand a higher return
on Apple stock, because its beta
is greater than for other stocks.
That's the core idea that underlies it.
Do you see that intuitively?
So, you have to change
your idea of what risk is.
Risk is covariance.
It's co-movements and not.
I have just one more slide here.
It's named after William Sharpe, who
is the inventor of the capital,
with Lintner, of the capital asset pricing model.
The Sharpe ratio is for any portfolio
that has a risk-free rate.
So, the average return on
the portfolio minus the risk-free rate
divided by the standard deviation of the portfolio.
And if you take the CAPM model,
the Sharpe ratio is constant along the tangency line.
This is a way of correcting the average return
from some investment for leverage.
So, companies used to advertise,
we've had a 15% average return.
And then investors would say,
but wait a minute, you didn't
tell me what your leverage is.
That's the first thing you should learn from this course.
Someone advertises that they had 15% return,
you say, ha, I want
to know what your leverage was.
I want to know, really, you know, how to,
you were just leveraging it up and taking big risks.
And on average, you'll do well, but it's risky.
So, this is the correction you make.
So, how do you correct for leverage?
Well, I want to look
at what fraction of the investor,
the investment portfolio is in the risky asset
and what fraction is in the riskless asset.
But it's not so easy to do that,
because the company can cover up its tracks.
It can invest in a company that's leveraged, right?
And so, you'd have to go one step further
and undo the leverage for that company.
It's hard to do that.
But the easy thing to do is just calculate
the Sharpe ratio for the investment company.
So, if some guy is investing,
and claiming to have done 15% of return
per year on his portfolio,
well, I'm going to look at the standard deviation
of the portfolio.
That's evidence of how leveraged this guy was.
And I'll compute the Sharpe ratio.
And unless it's bigger than the Sharpe ratio
for the, you know, the typical stock,
I don't, I'm not impressed.
Anyway, so, I think I've come
to an end of this lecture.
So, what you should have gotten from this lecture
is a concept of,
risk return trade-off,
a concept of optimal portfolio
as being something subtle and related to
Apollonius and Perga in difficult ways.
But there's also very simple things about
how to evaluate portfolio and portfolio managers
that comes out of this.